We had a major failure to one of our main computers and so that was a beyond my ability for sure,
but thanks to brother Jim and all of his hard work got that fixed and so that is
operating functioning properly this morning for which we are thankful. James chapter number four,
James chapter number four be looking at verses one through six this morning.
James chapter number four verses one through six and I'll read the text of scripture. We'll get
into the message this morning. I'm thankful that we have a bible amen and what a blessing and we're
thinking about it as we're there putting bibles together on Thursday about the mission of beacon
of truth to get the word of God to the entire world and thinking about those that do not have
bibles readily available for them and various projects that they've been able to engage in over
the years and opportunities that we have had as individuals as a church to be able to not only
give financially so that bibles could be printed but even to put our hand to the plow so to speak
and assemble the scriptures and that is a tremendous blessing every time we think about
opening our bible we ought to be thanking God that we have a bible and what a blessing. James
chapter number four the bible begins here look at verse one from whence come wars and fightings
among you come they not hence even of your lust that war in your members ye lust and have not
ye kill and desire to have and cannot obtain ye fight and war yet you have not because ye ask not
ye ask and receive not because you ask amiss that you may consume it upon your lust
ye adulterers and adulteresses know ye not that the friendship of the world
is enmity with God whosoever therefore will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God
do you think that the scripture saith in vain the spirit that dwelleth in us lusteth to envy
but he giveth more grace wherefore he saith God resisteth the proud but giveth grace
unto the humble this morning as we look at these six verses of scripture I want to
preach a message that I've titled from verse number six God giveth more grace and to be
honest with you there's several phrases within these six verses of scripture that you could use
as a title for a message as you're preaching through this text but I'm so thankful that we
serve a God who is gracious I'm so thankful that his grace is abundant we sing about God's amazing
grace and we ought to and we consider how that the apostle Paul often speaks of God's grace and
we understand this morning the grace of God as it's necessary for our salvation for our redemption
for by grace are you saved through faith and then we're mindful of the fact that God's grace
is given to us day by day really his sustaining grace or his enabling grace and it's mindful of
what Paul would be told by the Lord that he said my grace is sufficient for thee and we find that
Peter would say that we're to be good stewards of the manifold grace of God and Paul would say this
I know that I am what I am by the grace of God and our God is gracious and we ought to thank him for
his grace every day we find as we come to this text of scripture of course last Sunday morning
we examined the seven-fold description of the wisdom that is from above to conclude James
chapter number three we noted the contrast of God's wisdom to the counterfeit that was noted
in verses 15 and 16 we mentioned that as James would say that the wisdom that is from above and
we looked back at James chapter number one and understood that the Bible tells us that if any of
you lack wisdom let him ask of God who giveth to all men liberally and upbraideth not and what a
blessing to understand that every good gift and every perfect gift cometh from above right from
God and he says the wisdom that is from above and he gave us that seven-fold description he said it's
pure it's peaceable it's gentle easy to be entreated full of mercy and good fruits without
partiality and without hypocrisy what a great description and we said this we need that wisdom
we need God's wisdom and what a blessing to know that his wisdom is available to us as we begin
reading the fourth chapter and studying through this chapter of the book of James we find that
we are immediately confronted with some serious problems among the believers begin to consider
that here as we look at the summary that is provided for us with regard to the difficulties
the troubled times and the wars and fightings and the division and the carnality and all of those
things that are summarized in these first couple of verses of James chapter number four it's a sad
summary I would say this that the summary that's provided brings even more heartache when one
considers the biblical truth that as believers we are to walk in love we're to have fervent
charity among ourselves and we understand even on Wednesday evenings as we've been studying through
the little epistle of second John that he gives really three themes in that letter and the second
of those three themes is that we are to walk in love that we're to love one another we find that
that's oft repeated throughout the new testament and as we look here at the portion of scripture
and we know what's taking place we're obviously understanding that as James under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God concluded the third chapter that it really was giving way into the
fourth chapter with regard to remember that wisdom that descendeth not from above what did it bring
bitter envying strife right he talks about in verse number 16 for where envying and strife is
there is confusion and every evil work this wisdom it descendeth not from above it's earthly it's
sensual it's devilish and that's the counterfeit and he's really kind of laying the groundwork
for getting into chapter number four and dealing with the carnality and the division and all the
problems there within the text of scripture within the people of God
we must recognize this morning that God sees and knows everything
God sees and knows everything he knows those things that you think are kept secret maybe
personally within a family whatever it might be you say we're not gonna you ever heard the
phrase we're not gonna air our dirty laundry you ever hear somebody say that and what are they
talking about well they got some kind of dispute at home and they're not gonna make sure that
everyone else hears about it but you know God knows about that thing God's aware of it God sees
it God knows it and I would say this this morning that God provides correction so that God's people
can be all that he has called us to be and God's word is given to us the Bible says that it's
profitable for doctrine and I'm thankful for that but it's also profitable for reproof right that's
the rebuke that we need every once in a while we need to be corrected and God provides that
correction the people here of this these that James is writing to these people needed some
correction and God gives it to them and so as we notice the text of scripture I got four thoughts
for you this morning and I'll get through it quickly but I want you to see with me as we
consider these verses of scripture number one they're disappointing conduct they're disappointing
conduct notice remember if you will back in chapter number three in verse number 13
that that James said who's a wise man and in dude with knowledge among you let him show out of a
good conversation his works with meekness of wisdom and we've mentioned throughout our study of the
book of James that oftentimes James is focused on that outward conduct that behavior what we can see
why because what you truly believe impacts how you behave and you see me run from a snake when I
see one it's because I really believe that they're dangerous and you say but pastor that one's okay
I'm not going to find out amen and I'm just going to flee from that situation but we understand that
belief impacts behavior behavior reveals belief and as we look at the start of chapter number four
we find their disappointing conduct they were not doers of the word they were not walking in wisdom
they were not fulfilling the instruction that had been previously provided to them up to this point
in the book of James we find that our theme of course is that we're to be doers of the word
remember back in James chapter number one notice what James says in verse 19 leading up to our
theme verse of verse 22 in verse 19 the bible says wherefore my beloved brethren
let every man be swift to hear slow to speak slow to wrath now the context in chapter number three
is that they were swift to speak they they were not swift to hear and slow to speak they were
swift to speak everyone wanted to have that opportunity and they're not following the
instruction in verse 20 for the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God how many
of you have learned that in your life amen the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God
wherefore
Lay apart all filthiness and superfluity of naughtiness
and receive with meekness the engrafted word
which is able to save your souls.
Now, when we looked at this in chapter number one
months ago when we were studying through this chapter,
I mentioned to you that when James says
at the end of verse 21, which is able to save your souls,
he's not really talking about salvation redemption.
Although it is true that we're born again,
not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible
by the word of God which liveth and abideth forever,
he dealt with salvation previous to verse number 21.
He talks about in verse 18, of his own will
begat he us with the word of truth, amen.
We understand how can they hear without a preacher, right?
How are they gonna call on him in whom they've not heard?
In Romans chapter number 10, so then faith cometh
by hearing and hearing by the word of God.
Of his own will begat he us with the word of truth
that we should be a kind of first fruits of his creatures.
So we understand salvation in the place of God's word
with regard to salvation.
Listen, you must use the Bible when you're gonna
lead somebody to Christ.
It's absolutely essential.
The gospel tracts that we pass out,
they have the Bible in them.
They have the word of God.
When we pass out any little invitations,
we try very carefully.
There's occasionally when we have an invitation
that doesn't have the gospel on the back of it
and we accompany a gospel tract with it,
but we've tried with regard to the publishing materials
that we use that hey, we're giving out an invitation
for our special sunrise service on the back as the gospel.
Why?
Because the gospel is the power of God unto salvation
and the word of God is necessary.
But understand that in verse number 21,
when James says wherefore lay apart all filthiness
and superfluity of naughtiness and receive with meekness
the engrafted word which is able to save your souls,
I would say this.
He's not talking about salvation as he was in verse 18.
He's talking about saving you from a lot of trouble.
Can I tell you that God's word saves us
from a lot of trouble?
When we receive the word of God,
when we apply the word of God,
the way of transgressors is hard
according to the book of Proverbs.
And I have learned in my life of walking with the Lord
that the more I receive this word
and the more I apply this word,
the more it saves me from trouble and difficulty.
Listen, there's enough trouble and difficulty in the world
without me making my own through disobedience, right?
And we can make our own trouble through disobedience.
We can be in a place where we're doing things
that we're causing our own trouble,
but we find biblically that he says
that it will save our souls,
it will keep us from those difficulties.
Listen, they weren't following this.
Be doers, right?
You find in verse 22, but be doers of the word
and not hearers only deceiving your own selves.
And so the disappointing conduct that we read
in James chapter number four,
when he says from whence come wars and fighting among you.
And we begin to see this conduct of these individuals here
that James is writing to,
they were not following the word of God.
The word lust is used three times in three verses.
The word oftentimes in our kind of usage of the word today,
it would oftentimes think about the idea of sexual lust,
but understand the word means to have carnal desire,
to desire eagerly the gratification of carnal appetite,
to lust after something.
And we find that he talks here three times in three verses.
And we would say this and looking at their conduct,
their disappointing conduct
and adversely impacted relationships.
The relationships amongst the people of God
were not what they should be
or what they could be.
And we find that he says,
notice what he says in verse one,
from whence come wars and fightings,
notice this, among you, among you.
Come they not hence even of your lust
that war in your members.
Now the reality is that this conduct affects the individual,
but it also affects the whole,
there's private acts aspect of it
with regard to maybe even families
that are having this sort of situation with their conduct.
Then you have the situation as a family of God,
as a church, as believers.
And so we find that this conduct
was adversely impacting their relationships.
But it's very interesting in verse two and three,
that we would recognize that their conduct
was adversely impacting their prayer lives.
Notice in verse number two,
he says you lust and have not,
you kill and desire to have and cannot obtain.
You fight and war,
and then he says yet you have not because you ask not.
And so we find that their conduct,
their disappointing conduct,
the fact that they're dealing with all these things
and behaving in the way that they are,
they're trying to get everything by their own will,
by their own abilities.
Sometimes scheming and sometimes manipulating
and whatever it might be.
And God says you have not because you ask not.
And so how simple it is at times
when you consider the wonderful truth of prayer
that our God hears and answers prayer,
but we find that these people,
because of their carnality,
because of this disappointing conduct,
it was impacting their prayer
where they just simply weren't asking.
But then notice verse number three.
It's very interesting.
He says ye ask,
but you see in verse number two it says ye ask not.
Yeah, but there were some that were asking.
But they too weren't having their prayers answered.
Why?
Because they ask amiss.
Notice what it says that ye may consume it upon your lust.
Can I tell you this morning that not every prayer
is a prayer that's pleasing to God.
You can pray and I can pray selfishly.
We can pray for our own good.
You know, we ought to pray for God's glory.
Amen?
We ought to pray that he would be glorified,
that he would be the one that would receive
the reverence that is due
and the recognition for what he's done.
And we find that he says that their prayer lives
had been adversely impacted because of this conduct.
And it all really begins with the fact
that they're not doers of the word.
You know, the reality this morning,
the sad reality if you read chapter one,
verses 18 through 22,
is that you can be saved by the word of God,
but not live according to the word of God.
Just because you're saved doesn't mean
that you're automatically gonna apply God's word
in your life and live a life of obedience.
It's a choice that you make,
that we're gonna take this
and we're gonna apply this in our lives,
that we're gonna follow the truth,
the commandments that God has given to us.
Their disappointing conduct leads us to number two,
their destructive conflicts.
We see their disappointing conduct,
but then we know their destructive conflicts.
Again, these would be personally,
these would be corporately.
Notice the Bible says from whence,
notice the words that are used.
From whence come wars and fightings among you.
He says in verse number two,
you lust and have not, ye kill and desire to have.
And you begin to see these destructive conflicts
that are active and present here
within those that James is writing to.
And this is not, look at, I mean,
remember last week, the wisdom that's from above.
If we're walking in wisdom, it's pure,
it's peaceable, it's gentle.
No, no, there's an absence of that true wisdom.
Although in the very beginning of the book,
God told the people through James,
if you lack, ask and he'll give it.
And yet they're operating,
they're living without what God offers.
Isn't that sad?
Sometimes we do the same thing.
God offers us the answers, God offers us the wisdom.
And we're just gonna kind of rise up
and we're gonna be prideful
and we're going to know I'm gonna do it this way
and you don't understand what they did
or whatever it might be
and we allow this thing to get out of hand.
Reminds me a lot of the church in Corinth.
A church that was carnal, a church that was divisions
and all of these fightings and things that were going on.
Paul says it's reported and I believe it.
Think about that, amen.
And we begin to think about what James said in James three
and I know it's not the context of this,
but I wanna apply it when James is writing these things
in these first few verses of James four.
He said this in James three in verse number 10,
out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing.
Notice where he says, my brethren,
these things ought not so to be.
Now he doesn't say that in chapter four in verse number three
but I certainly think you could.
Wars, fightings, my brethren,
these things ought not to be, amen.
And we find, think about this,
turn back to the book of Genesis, if you will, chapter 13.
We'll look at Genesis, I'm gonna look over
in the book of Acts as well,
but look in Genesis chapter 13
and I want you to see here,
contextually there's this conversation that takes place
between Abram and Lot.
And we find that.
within the context you find there's growth and what have you with regard to the blessing
of the Lord and you understand that there's going to be this separation as you go through
the chapter. But what really leads to the conversation is given to us in verse number
7. The Bible says this, and there was a strife between the herdmen of Abram's cattle and
the herdmen of Lot's cattle. So there's a strife, there's a problem, there's a situation.
Now I don't know all that it was, it doesn't tell us, but it does give us a very important
point of emphasis at the end of verse number 7. Notice what the Bible says, and the herd,
it says this, and the Canaanite and the Perizzite dwelt then in the land. Can I tell you something
this morning? James chapter number 3 is talking about Christians. Sorry, chapter 4. Talking
about Christians. First Corinthians, talking about a church. A church is made up of believers.
We understand that Genesis chapter 13 is talking about individuals and their people that are
responsible, Abram and Lot family, right? So different than the church. But I want you
to think about this. He said, he gave us this detail that the Canaanite and the Perizzite
dwelt then in the land. Can I equate that to lost people? Would that be okay if I make
that application? So you know what lost people are looking at when they see God's people
fighting and arguing? Why do I need your God? You talk to me about reconciliation and you
can't be reconciled in your own relationships. Right? My brethren, these things ought not
so to be. I know again that's James 3.10, but man it applies. He said the Canaanite
and the Perizzite are here. And Abram's herdmen and Lot's herdmen, they're having this strife.
And this isn't right. Listen, if anybody ought to be able to get together and get along it
ought to be the people of God. Amen? We ought to be able to walk in unity. In our homes
we ought to be able to have unity in our homes. We preached last year from 2 Corinthians chapter
number 5 the fact that we've been given this ministry of reconciliation. And how am I going
to go tell somebody how they can be reconciled to God, but I can't be reconciled with my
own family member, with my own church member? Do you understand what I'm saying? And so
what happens in verse 8? And Abram said unto Lot, Lotus, let there be no strife I pray
thee between me and thee and between my herdmen and thy herdmen. Then notice the last four
words for we be, tell me what it says? Brethren. For we be brethren. Listen a church should
never have the reputation or the testimony of having fightings and wars among them. Amen?
Your family and my family should never have that testimony of, I'm just saying it ought
not be. Now I understand every single person has a responsibility, an individual responsibility.
But we look here, look over in Acts chapter number 7, look in Acts chapter 7. In this
passage of scripture Stephen is preaching and what a great message he preaches by the
way. And we find that the Bible is talking to us in the beginning part of the message
he's talking about Moses and notice in verse 23 of Acts chapter number 7 and when he, that's
Moses, was full 40 years old it came into his heart to visit his brethren, the children
of Israel. And seeing one of them suffer wrong he defended him and avenged him that was oppressed
and smote the Egyptian. Now Moses thought he was doing what was right. Notice verse
25, for he supposed his brethren would have understood how that God by his hand would
deliver them but they understood not. Now there's a lot of truth in verse 25. Sometimes
you assume somebody understands and they don't. Notice what it says, he supposed his
brethren would have understood how that God by his hand would deliver them. You ever been
in a situation where somebody says, well I just thought you should read my mind. I am
not a mind reader and neither are you. Come on. You know what I'm saying? Don't suppose
that somebody understands. You make sure that they understand. Communication is two way.
With my kids all the time Joe says, why do you keep asking me do I understand? Because
everywhere, every now and then in the middle of this conversation I want to make sure you
understand what I'm saying. Right? That's why it's helpful sometimes when somebody says
amen when you're preaching. Why? Because that means I'm with you, I got it, I agree. We're
tracking. Sometimes when you're up here looking from this way you look at somebody and you're
like, they're not hearing a word I'm saying. They're thinking about I don't know what they're
thinking about but they are out to lunch man. You know what I'm saying? And if you don't
know what I'm saying I'll let you preach next week and you can see it alright. But here's
the deal. It's good to make sure people understand not to assume because it says they understood
not. They understood not. Then look at the next verse in verse 26. And the next day he
showed himself unto them as they strove and would have set them at one again. So now there's
another strife right? And it says sirs you're brethren. Why do ye wrong one to another?
What did Abram say? We are brethren. Right? Here Moses says you're brethren. Why do ye
wrong one to another? These are great questions and great examples that we see in the book
of Genesis and the book of Acts with regard to other records that God gives us and we
look here in the book of James and we see this situation in chapter number four and
we understand their conduct and then we see their conflicts. Listen I'll just be honest
with you this morning. I like it when there's no conflicts. Amen? I like it when we sing
the song there's nothing between my soul and my Savior and we ought to be in that position
where we're right with God. But we understand as much as we ought to be right with God we
ought to be right one with another. And I would submit to you biblically if you were
to look at a whole lot of scripture you're not really right with God if you're not right
with your brethren. Amen? How do you say you love God and you haven't seen him but you
don't love your brethren that you see? James? Sorry, 1 John? And look at what Paul said
you don't have to turn there but in Acts 24 and verse 16 and herein do I exercise myself
to have always a conscience void of offense toward God and toward men. It's an important
thing. People talk about the relationship between us vertically with God but the relationship
between us horizontally with our brethren. And if I'm not right here it's really a hard
thing for me to be right here. James chapter number four we see their conduct we see their
conflicts. Notice with me number three the devastating conclusion. Devastating conclusion
we see it in verse number four. The indictment is clear it's powerful. The root of all that
has been outlined in the first three verses is going to be exposed very plainly. The worldliness
and the carnality. We find that God would use the verbiage and the words that would
relate and communicate spiritual adultery. This is something that was so prominent in
the Old Testament when they would go after idols and God would deal with that. You read
the book of Hosea and study through the book of Hosea and repeatedly God's dealing with
that theme. And we find now in the New Testament, remember 1 John ends this way, keep yourselves
from idols. Sometimes we think man we don't have idols today like they had. And they might
be a lot different but man there's idols today. There are a lot of things that become idols.
The Bible says in Colossians chapter number one that in all things he might have the preeminence
that's God. That he might have the preeminence. Anything that takes place where God should
be is an idol. It's an idol. And so we find this worldliness. Notice he says ye adulterers
and adulteresses. The language is strong and the indictment is powerful. It's clear. He
says know ye not that the friendship of the world is enmity with God. Whosoever therefore
will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God. That is strong language. And it's
very plain language. We find as we look here at this portion of Scripture we're reminded
that we're in the world but we're not of the world. We're reminded that we're to come out
from among them and be separate saith the Lord. We're reminded of this important aspect
that you cannot serve God and mammon. A double minded man is unstable in all his ways. In
fact you'll find that in chapter number four in verse number eight he talks about their
double mindedness. We'll get to that in our next message. But I want you to understand
that our God is a jealous God. Our God is a jealous God. See when God brought his people
out of Egypt and he brought them into the land of promise he told them listen don't
behave like what you witnessed in Egypt and don't behave like you're going to see the
behavior of those in the land. Why? Because you're my people. And I'm a jealous God. He
tells us in the old
in the Old Testament of that truth,
and we see that played out in the life of Israel,
in the people of God, and you see all of their error,
and it's all exposed for us,
and we find the New Testament teaching for us
as the people of God is this principle
that we often refer to as put off and put on.
That we're to put off the old, we're to put on the new.
That we're to walk as the children of light, why?
Because we are.
We don't handle the disputes,
we don't handle the conflict and the contention
the same way that we used to, why?
Because we're different.
We've been saved by the grace of God.
I've heard people over the years,
in fact, I had a pastor,
and I'll use him as a personal example.
Our pastor, the man that we served with
before we came here 15 years ago,
he is a great preacher,
and we find that he was an Italian man,
full-blooded Italian,
and oftentimes he'd talk about how,
as an Italian, he had a temper.
And some of you are smiling, maybe you can relate,
maybe you know, I don't have, as far as I know,
I have no Italian in me,
but that was his little thing,
he'd say it all the time, right?
You know why that bothered me?
I'm not trying to correct him,
especially when I sat under him,
but the Bible says if any man be in Christ,
he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away,
behold, all things are become new.
It doesn't mean that that, quote-unquote,
as he would refer to it, Italian blood didn't rage up,
but it meant that he had another spirit living within him
that would allow him to walk in victory.
Amen?
And so these people that have been saved,
listen, when we were lost,
we may have handled certain things a certain way.
When somebody wronged us,
we may have dealt with it a certain way,
but now that we're the people of God,
the fact that Christ lives in us
and the fact that he's called us to this newness of life
and to walk in the ways of the Lord,
listen, he gave us an example when he was reviled,
the Bible says he reviled not again.
It's different now.
And God says the problem,
the reason that you're behaving the way that you're behaving
is because you're worldly.
You're behaving the way that you're behaving
because you love the world
and you have all of that worldliness
and all that carnality in you, and guess what?
That's what's coming out.
Do we see it in our society?
How do people handle conflict today?
I mean, literally,
you think about how people handle conflict today.
They wanna kill each other.
Right?
It's insane.
I say this all the time.
If I have an opportunity,
as I've had an opportunity a couple of times recently
to have pre-marriage counseling,
one of the sessions that we deal with
in pre-marriage counseling is conflict resolution.
And one of the things that I always say in that first,
in the very beginning of that lesson is this,
the world does not know how to resolve conflict.
They just don't.
But God's people ought to be able to resolve conflict,
and we ought to be able to resolve it to the glory of God.
Amen?
Listen, in Romans chapter 12,
look what the Bible says in Romans chapter 12.
We're familiar with it,
but I want you to see it and read it
and just allow it to penetrate our hearts this morning.
The Bible in Romans chapter 12,
Paul is writing to these people.
He's laid really a great,
just a book that's so detailed and outlined
with regard to coming to this conclusion.
In verse number 12, listen,
all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
You're lost and undone,
but God's grace and God's mercy.
And you get to chapter five and six
and think about the gift of God,
which is eternal life.
In chapter number 10,
for whoso shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
And thinking about being saved by the grace of God
and all that he did for us.
And he says in chapter 12, in verse number one,
I beseech you, therefore brethren.
The interesting aspect of this verse of scripture
is it starts with the basis of begging.
I beseech you.
We understand who he's speaking to believers
because he says brethren,
but it's interesting that he uses that word therefore.
All that I've just laid all of this argument,
these 11 chapters brings us to this point.
I beseech you therefore, brethren,
by the mercies of God,
that you present your body as a living sacrifice,
wholly acceptable unto God,
which is your reasonable service
and be not conformed to this world,
but be transformed by the renewing of your mind
that you may prove what is that good
and acceptable and perfect will of God.
Be not conformed to this world,
but be transformed by the renewing of your mind.
You know, what's interesting about this admonition,
this instruction is that we came out of the world.
So, you know, it's really easy for us to be worldly.
It's our nature.
And the older you were when you got saved,
the harder it is because it's your nature.
And we find that he says that we're not to be conformed.
Why?
Because we're different now.
We've been saved.
And we don't have, listen, I'm no longer bound by sin.
How many are thankful for that?
Praise God.
But thanks be to God which giveth us the victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find he says by the renewing of your mind,
how do we renew our mind?
It's through the word of God.
It's the place of God's word in my life
of renewing my mind.
And you know what these people needed?
They needed this devastating conclusion
that is given to us with regard to their spiritual adultery,
to their worldliness, to their carnality.
They really need the truth of Romans 12 verses one and two.
They need the truth and we looked at it last week
of 1 John chapter number two in verses 15 through 17
when he says love not the world,
neither the things that are in the world.
And then he tells them this,
if any man love the world,
the love of the Father is not in him.
Don't fight with me, fight with God.
It's God's word.
Amen.
And then he tells us this,
I love the truth of verse 15,
but I love the explanation of verse 16 and 17.
It says for all that is in the world,
the lust of the flesh and the lust of the eyes
and the pride of life is not of the Father,
but is of the world.
And then he tells us this in verse 17 of 1 John two,
and the world passeth away and the lust thereof.
But he that doeth the will of God abideth forever.
Do you wanna be part of something that's going to endure
or something that's gonna just be temporal, just pass by?
And he tells us, he makes it plain for us here
in 1 John chapter two verses 15 through 17
of this situation.
Listen, you know, it's a problem today in our world
where the church is trying to be like the world.
How many churches trying to adapt things from the world
and try to, listen, if we wanna reach the world,
we gotta be like the world.
That's not biblical.
That's not what God's word says.
I have it referenced, we're not gonna turn there,
but 2 Corinthians chapter six,
you read through the end of the chapter,
the beginning of chapter seven,
come out from among them and be you separate,
sayeth the Lord.
Listen, and by the way,
the world's not looking for some cheap imitation.
They're not looking for some cheap imitation.
They're looking for something that's real.
Can I tell you that our God is real?
When you come to a place and God is there
and God's word is proclaimed, listen, that's,
that's what it's about.
I know the illustration has been used before,
but I think it's an important understanding for us
when we think about worldliness.
Sometimes when we think about worldliness,
we think about it in our modern context of today.
Well, I want you to just think,
and some of you here are a lot older than I am,
and I don't say that in a negative way,
I just say it realistically.
There are several people here that are younger than I am.
There are several people here today
that I could say something that happened in my childhood
and they weren't even close to being alive, I get it.
But I want you to think about where America is today
and where America was when you were a kid.
Has it changed?
Has it gotten worse?
I'm 46 years old, right?
I'm not that old, but I'm kind of in that unknown stage,
honestly, like it's like, are you, what are you?
My brother keeps trying to tell me certain things
of being old and so on and so forth,
but you're kind of in this middle range, whatever.
But look, things have changed a lot in my lifetime.
And some of you have been alive longer than me.
You remember when there was a time in our nation
where there was prayer in school, Bible in school,
when there was a time that the Ten Commandments
were posted in certain places publicly, right?
We remember those things.
I don't remember those.
I remember reading about those things.
I remember when there was a lot of sin that was being done,
but it was shameful.
It wasn't celebrated, it was shameful, right?
The world's changed.
And here's what I'm afraid of,
and I'm gonna use the illustration geographically,
if you'd allow me to do that.
We understand this idea of separation, it's important.
But if we could take,
and I'm not gonna go through all the cities,
but if we could just take New York City,
and think about being on the eastern seaboard
of the United States,
and then let's take Philadelphia, all right?
So it's still on the east,
it's some distance away from New York City,
and you think about that, and there's a division there.
And if we could look at that,
and say that the worldliness is Philadelphia,
and godliness is New York City,
that's a terrible illustration, that's really bad.
But let's just, for example, say geographically,
so you can get in your mind,
if you say, I'm terrible at geography,
just bear with me, all right?
What's happened is the world went from Philly to Pittsburgh,
and the church went from New York to Philly.
Are you tracking?
And then what happened is the church was there in Philly,
and the world was in Pittsburgh,
and there was separation.
But really, there was a lot of worldliness in the church,
a lot of carnality in the church.
And then the world went to Chicago, further west yet.
You know what the church did?
Went to Pittsburgh.
So guess what?
There's a lot of worldliness in the church,
a lot of carnality in the church.
The church says, no, no, we're not like that.
Look at how, we're different than them.
Yeah, but are we what we're supposed to be?
And you could just keep doing that until you get to LA.
All right?
And we're not gonna keep doing that.
I think you get the idea this morning.
But what I'm saying is that we don't look at worldliness
based on the context in where we live today.
We look at worldliness based on the context
of what does God's word say is worldly.
That's how we define worldliness,
not by what's worldly today.
By the way, there are churches today,
quote unquote churches today,
that are doing some egregious, wicked things.
I drove by a church over going to a Zachary soccer game
a couple of years ago.
I don't even know the name of that Baptist church over there.
They got pride flags hanging on their church building.
Say it's a Baptist church.
Almost made me get in a car accident.
I'm serious, man.
I was like, what in the,
but I'm driving this way, you know?
And I'm like, what in the world?
There's a church down in a church,
quote unquote, down in Richmond.
Baptist church in Richmond.
They had drag shows at their church last summer.
And you say, yeah, that's disgusting.
It's shameful.
It's insane.
It's a problem.
We see it in James.
We see this devastating conclusion.
And when you look at this, you say, look,
God's showing the people like, hey,
this is the worldliness.
Can I remind you, if you were to look back
at the period of the kings,
sin is a slippery slope.
It's a slippery slope.
Worldliness and carnality is slippery.
You start letting that thing kind of go a little bit,
what do they say?
You give them an inch and they take a,
hmm, you know it, right?
I don't think the kings ever intended
to sacrifice their children to Molech.
But it's recorded that they did.
You say, how in the world?
You knew the one God, Jehovah.
How did you get there?
Well, it's just one step at a time.
But it's a slippery slope.
And can I tell you that slippery slope,
like the snowball analogy that we've all seen,
that slippery slope, you get to a point
where it's just downhill, quick.
All of a sudden, decisions are being made
and you're saying, how do we get here?
How did this happen?
How did that happen at that place?
And you get, and it's worldliness.
How's that happen in our home, in our family?
I've said many times over the years
that a solid biblical church is made up
of solid biblical families.
And solid biblical families are made up
of solid biblical individuals, amen?
And that's why it's so important
that every single one of us as individual believers
are walking with God.
So we see, as we've looked here so far through the text,
we notice the disappointing, their disappointing conduct,
their destructive conflicts, the devastating conclusion.
But I want you to see in verses five and six,
the divine cure, the divine cure.
I was gonna stop in verse number four
and God just wouldn't let me.
And I'm gonna tell you that as I touch on verses five and six
it's really just an introduction to next week's message.
Because the following text of scripture,
really verses seven through 10,
further develop and explain the cure in its completeness.
Verse number five and six just kinda gives you the preview,
if you will, to the fullness,
to the completeness of the divine cure.
When we love the world, we grieve the Holy Spirit.
Because he said, if you love the world,
whosoever therefore will be a friend of the world
is the enemy of God.
If you love the world,
then the love of the Father is not in you.
And so we begin to understand here
with regard to this understanding of verse number five,
that listen, when I love the world,
when I'm a friend of the world,
then I grieve the Holy Spirit.
The Bible says that we're to quench not the spirit,
that we're to grieve not the spirit.
Can I tell you this morning
that all of us that have been saved by the grace of God,
we have all of him, and he wants all of us.
I'm thankful that I have all of the Holy Spirit,
but the Holy Spirit wants all of me.
Teaching in Sunday school this morning,
I was teaching about 10 life lessons,
it's gonna take us 10 weeks to go through these things,
but one of the lesson for today was about
wholly or completely following the Lord.
And I asked this question, how do we do that?
One person said this, surrender.
I said, bingo, that's the key.
We were gonna get there to Mark chapter eight,
as eventually we were gonna end up.
And they said that answer,
and he said, listen, it's all about surrender, yielding.
We have all of the Holy Spirit,
but the Holy Spirit wants all of us.
And our God is a jealous God, and he wants all of us.
He wants us to have, as we read in Romans chapter 12,
to present our bodies a living sacrifice,
holy, acceptable unto God,
which is your reasonable service.
But we look at that in Romans chapter 12
at the end of verse number one,
that's the super Christian.
But God says that's just reasonable service.
When I truly understand all that he's done for me,
how could I not wanna live for him?
We come to that place of recognizing
that the friendship and the love of the world
is enmity with God, but it grieves the Holy Spirit,
and we have all of him, and he wants all of us.
And I would say that humility is required.
In verse number six, the Bible says,
but he giveth more grace.
Wherefore, he saith, God resisteth the proud,
but giveth grace unto the humble.
Humility is required.
Humility to acknowledge how our conduct
is both wrong and destructive.
I shared with you, after I went to a pastor's meeting
a year ago, how this man stood up and made this comment
that he'd been married for 35 years or something,
and never had an argument one time with his wife,
never said anything, never raised his voice one time,
and he was talking about all this kind of stuff,
and then he said this, there were plenty of times
that I just didn't talk.
Listen, that's not any better.
Amen?
That's not resolving conflict.
Silent treatment is not godly.
Well, I'm glad you didn't say something
that's gonna get you in trouble,
but that's not the right response.
So what does humility do?
Well, humility acknowledges that my conduct is wrong
and my conduct is destructive as I humble myself
and I come before the Lord, I humble myself before the Lord,
but if there's that conflict in those wars
and those fightings, what does the book of Proverbs tell us?
It says, only by pride cometh contention.
There's a lot of contention here amongst these,
and there was a need for humility.
Why?
Because God resisteth the proud,
but giveth grace unto the humble.
And we see that necessity for humility
and how it's required, and listen,
humility will lead to confession.
Humility will lead to reconciliation.
Humility will lead to healing.
It will.
Pride, not gonna lead to any of those things.
Let me tell you how you were wrong.
Not a good way to start.
Right?
Because, humility is that, let a man examine himself.
First Corinthians 11.
And I stand before the Lord and I say, Lord, would you help me to be humble?
Because I need your grace.
God, there's this situation over here and maybe truly the other person was definitely
more wrong than I was, but God, how did I not handle it right?
God, what could I have done?
How could I handle this?
God, would you give me grace so that we can see this thing resolved?
Amen?
I say this often, again, to use the idea of pre-marriage counseling.
Listen, if the two become one, and that's what the Bible says, right?
Two become one, yes or no?
Amen?
So if I hurt my spouse, if I hurt Holly, I love her, she's my wife, 25 years, but if
I hurt her, you know what?
I'm hurting myself.
Right?
If she hurts me, she's hurting herself.
Yes, we're hurting our relationship, but we're hurting, like it doesn't make any sense.
Now it doesn't mean that just because it doesn't make any sense that there's not going to ever
be a conflict.
Amen?
But when there's conflict, there needs to be humility.
And so that's in the home, but it's also in the church.
We're all different.
Come from different backgrounds.
One of the things that's so challenging about marriage, you've got people that are coming
from two different homes and two different styles of everything, and they come together
as one, but with God's help and by God's grace.
A church, we're many members, right, individuals, but we're brought together as a single body.
And you come in, and I've used the phraseology, when there's new sheep in the pen, quote unquote,
because God refers to us as sheep.
And you introduce a new sheep into the pen, and guess what?
There's some, every once in a while, there's some challenges that are created because of
that.
But those challenges don't have to turn into conflicts and turn into, you know why?
Because we're going to humble ourselves.
This is the divine cure that God gives us.
There needs to be that humility.
And not only will the humility lead to confession and reconciliation and healing, but most importantly
we see that we receive God's grace.
God's grace.
I need God's grace.
You need God's grace.
We spoke about wisdom.
We need God's wisdom.
Absolutely.
But I need the grace of God, and so do you.
And I'm thankful that God gives it, but we see the truth that it says, God resisteth
the proud.
Listen, if you're prideful this morning, if there's some kind of conflict, whether it's
that conflict that we're not airing our dirty laundry, as I mentioned early on, if there's
conflict, God's not pleased with that.
And God's resisting the one that's prideful.
So at what point are we going to humble ourselves?
Say, God, I don't want all this.
I don't want to operate worldly.
I don't want to operate based on, like my former pastor would say, well, I'm Italian,
that's just how we deal with it.
No, no, no.
We're Christians now.
Amen?
And we're in Christ, and therefore we're to be different.
And so as many titles as I could have given to the message this morning, I want to focus
on that one, that God giveth more grace, because our God is a gracious God.
As far as I know, there's no, like, big conflicts in our church amongst our body, and I'm thankful
for that.
But I don't have my head in the sand to know that that couldn't happen.
I don't know.
There might be some conflicts personally that no one else knows about, but you do, and God
does.
He knows everything.
He sees everything.
And it'd be far better to get that thing resolved, and to have God's grace, and to be able to
move forward for the glory of God, than to continue hurting yourself and those that are
dearest to you.
Amen?
Amen.
God giveth more grace, and every one of us ought to thank God for His grace.
Let us pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
I thank You for the Word of God.
Lord, this morning, the Holy Spirit takes and ministers to each individual as only He
can.
And God, maybe this morning there's some things that I don't know about, but God, You do.
I pray that we would, unlike these original recipients who refuse to submit to the Word
of God, and to be doers of the Word, would You help us this morning to submit to You,
to Your Word.
Help us to be doers.
I pray that in the quiet moments of invitation that You would have Your perfect will and
I pray, God, that You would give us that grace that we so desperately need.
Well thank You, God, for what You'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.